<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The great efficacy and necessity of good example especially in the clergy recommended in a visitation sermon preached at Guilford / by Tho. Duncumb ...</title>
            <author>Duncumb, Thomas, d. 1714?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1671</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 74 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A36889</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D2610</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R22681</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12572090</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12572090</idno>
            <idno type="VID">63490</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A36889)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 63490)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 314:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The great efficacy and necessity of good example especially in the clergy recommended in a visitation sermon preached at Guilford / by Tho. Duncumb ...</title>
                  <author>Duncumb, Thomas, d. 1714?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 31, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by John Winter for William Cadman ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1671.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata on p. [2] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Visitation sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English.</term>
               <term>Clergy --  Religious life.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:63490:1"/>
            <p>THE GREAT <hi>EFFICACY</hi> and <hi>NECESSITY</hi> OF GOOD EXAMPLE Eſpecially in the CLERGY: Recommended in a Viſitation Sermon Preached at GUILFORD.</p>
            <p>By <hi>THO. D<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NC<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>MB,</hi> Maſter of Arts, Sometimes Fellow of <hi>Corpus Chriſti</hi> Colledge in <hi>Oxford,</hi> and now Rector of <hi>Shere</hi> in <hi>Surrey.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2 Tit. 7, 8.</hi>
               </bibl> In all things ſhewing thy ſelf a pattern of good Works in Doctrine ſhewing uncorruptneſs, gravity, ſincerity; ſound ſpeech, that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be condemned; that he, that is of the contrary part, may be aſhamed, having no evil thing to ſay of you.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>S. Hieronymus.</hi>
               </bibl> Vehementer Eccleſiam Dei deſtruit, meliores Laicos eſſe quam Clericos.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>John Winter,</hi> for <hi>William Cad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>an,</hi> at the <hi>Pope</hi>'s <hi>Head</hi> in the <hi>New-Exchange</hi> in the <hi>Strand.</hi> 1671.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:63490:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:63490:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Right Honourable and Reverend Father in God, GEORGE, Lord Biſhop of WINCHESTER, AND Prelate of the moſt Noble Order of the GARTER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THis Diſcourſe which I have preſum'd, <hi>more at large,</hi> to venture in the world under your Lordſhips Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage, I muſt freely acknowledge I firſt fetch't it, <hi>more compendiouſly,</hi> from your ſelf, under your Lordſhips own Roof; where <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is well as in the Pulpit, and in Publ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ck it cannot eaſily eſcape the Notice of any (who will not wilfull, ſhut their eyes) how much your vigorous Diſcourſes, your important Counſels, your active Endeavours, and conſtant Encouragements, all concur to <hi>make</hi> and <hi>keep</hi> an Exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary Clergie; ſuch, I mean; as may be a more viſible grace to the Goſpel, a greater Credit to the Church, a Bleſſing to the King and Kingdom, and a more lively Repreſentation of the life of Christ (the foundation of all.)</p>
            <p>And indeed, the preſent Age we live in, ſeems to out-do all before it, in its louder Calls for ſuch a Clergie, whoſe L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ves may be obſerv'd to keep ſome better pace with their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines; and not ſo much to fail and lurch the but juſt and reaſonable expectations of the People; whilſt they diſcover ſome amongſt us, whoſe Lives, too too often prove (as it were) the death of <hi>that,</hi> they ſeem to preſs, with more than ordinary zeal, and concernedneſs, upon others.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:63490:3"/>
            <p>My Lord; Its <hi>now</hi> become no hard matter to find ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of our Hearers, as it were, dead under the weight of our numerous Sermons; and there being nothing ſo probably effectual, to fetch them back to life again, as the more kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly quickning influence, they may all fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l from our own walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more, as burning and ſhining lights amongſt them; I ſoon concluded this ſubject, very anſwerable to ſo important a deſign; a Subject, indeed, which gave me the greater pleaſure and ſatisfaction in my own reflection upon it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, whilst it but <hi>Teaches</hi> and <hi>Inſtructs</hi> [many of us, the meaner Servants of the Altar] it ſeems only to be a fairer Deſcription of your Self. I know not what reception this plain Sermon may meet withal from ſome in the world; but, if any ſhall pleaſe themſelves, in making me an example of their Contempt and Deriſion, for being ſo dull in my Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, for the awakening others, to their being better ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples in their Lives; I ſhall take the ſame liberty again, to pleaſe my ſelf in my own private ſenſe and Reflections, with what ſober and ſincere ends, I firſt <hi>gave this Diſcourſe (ſuch as it is)</hi> from the Pulpit; and now, have, (not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out your Lordſhips own ſignal approbation) given it to the Preſs, which, indeed, I have done (next to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of God, and the hopes, at leaſt, of ſome ſmall additions to the publick good) from no greater motive, or inclination, than to profeſs and acknowledge my ſelf, not only within the ſphere of your Lordſhips own Dioceſs, but, to the whole world, how much I really am,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Lordſhips moſt humbly devoted Servant, in all Dutiful Obſervance,</hi> Tho. Duncumb.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>October 14th. <hi>1670.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:63490:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 TIM. 4.12.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>Let no man deſpiſe thy youth, but be thou an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Believers in Word, in Converſation, in Charity, in Spirit, in Faith, in Purity.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Aint <hi>Paul</hi> having in his earlier years prov'd a moſt ſevere and cruel Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to Chriſtianity, of a bloody Perſecutor, afterwards becomes a bleſſed Promoter of its oppoſed Intereſt and Reputation in the World.</p>
            <p>He had not been, of old, ſo zealous in his alarms and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated animations of the Jews againſt Chriſt and his Croſs, but afterwards he is as indefatigably ſollicitous to calm and allay all thoſe Storms and Tempeſts, all thoſe Popular Furies and Eſtuations he had formerly rais'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them.</p>
            <p>Hence (over and above all his own publick, perſonal, and moſt painful preaching) he diſpatches, ſo many pious Epiſtles, and endeavours the Diſciplining of ſo many ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected Perſons (as we finde he hath done) that ſo what
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:63490:4"/> ſervice he could not do, immediately in his own perſon, for Chriſt, and the Chriſtian profeſſion, that might be done by ſuch <hi>Proxies</hi> and Epiſtolary preparations, as he thought moſt expedient and conducing to ſo excellent an end and purpoſe.</p>
            <p>The Epiſtle and Perſon wherein my Text is concern'd, are both the deſigned Inſtruments of this great Chriſtian Convert, St. <hi>Paul,</hi> for the more effectual carrying on and accompliſhing of this ſo great and important an En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprize.</p>
            <p>Now that he may not loſe his Labour, nor have his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectations fail him in an Affair of ſo great a Value and Conſideration; like a wiſe Agent, he firſt ſolidly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſults the true and timely Adaptation of his Medium, for the more ſure and ſucceſsful accompliſhment of this his propounded End: And therefore in this Epiſtle, (as well as in that other to <hi>Timothy,</hi> at that time Biſhop of <hi>Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi>) he gives him many ſolid and ſound Inſtructions, rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting both to the Doctrine and Diſcipline of this his grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Charge and Dioceſs. But now, becauſe neither the one, nor the other; neither the choiceſt Doctrine, nor yet the ſtricteſt Diſcipline, were like to benefit or advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage others,<note place="margin">Effice pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis moribus &amp; incu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta vita, ut ne quis Te, contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem tuae adoleſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat, <hi>ſaith</hi> Clarius. Fac ut mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitate, tan tum reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentia tibi concilies, ne quid at as tua jnvenilis, qua alioqui contemptui obnoxia eſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſolet, tua au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritate minuat. <hi>Calv.</hi>
               </note> unleſs <hi>Timothy</hi> (who was to actuate and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force them) were a good Example himſelf; St. <hi>Paul</hi> in the firſt place, ſees himſelf concern'd to counſel and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe <hi>Timothy,</hi> to ſuch an exemplary Carriage and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portment, in this his Place and more ſacred Employment, as that, the World's Reflection upon him, in that, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, undervalued circumſtance of youth, may give the greater cauſe to look upon him as worthy of double Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and to eſteem him too, very highly for his Works ſake, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.17. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.13.</p>
            <p>Some Vegetables, the younger and tenderer they are, the greater ſweetneſs and fragrancy they commonly breathe forth and tranſmit into all the reſpective parts of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:63490:4"/> that place, where they are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> which then ſmells ſweeteſt, when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> And thus it ſeems St. <hi>Paul,</hi> would have his young <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> (like a <hi>Roſe of Sharon</hi> by him planted in the <hi>Epheſian</hi> ſoil) to have ſo great a flavor in the bud, at that he may, even then appear and approve himſelf to be unto God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſavour of Chriſt, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.15. and unto men of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity in its greateſt Power and Purity. <hi>Let no man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſpiſe thy Youth.</hi>—
<q>But be thou an Example of the Believers:</q>
            </p>
            <p>That is, It's not enough for thee to content thy ſelf with being a bare Example of meerly moral civiliz'd men, (though this be very valuable in it ſelf) but rather raiſe thy Soul to ſome higher pitch of Piety and Profeſſion, and look upon thy ſelf (eſpecially in the place where thou art) as highly concern'd to be, no leſs than a lively Pattern too, of the nobler and more excellent Perſons, even of the Believers, thoſe Heav'n-born Souls, thoſe bright and ſparkling Jewels of Heavens Boſom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of whom the World is not worthy, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.38. and who keep themſelves un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpotted from the World, <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.29. Theſe theſe are the Darlings of Heaven whom thou art carefully to teach, and to build up more and more in their moſt holy faith, by thy own more holy and exemplary Lift: Thou art to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> them all ſuch an exact Copy and Tranſcript of an heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Nature and Diſpoſition, as that thou mayſt not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>em to lack any part or particular appertaining to it, but rather whatſoever it really is, in Word, whatſoever in Charity, in Spirit, in Faith, and in Purity, than eſpecially thou ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> bound to ſhew, and to confirm Believers in by way of Eminency.</p>
            <p>It ſeems, by all this, St. <hi>Paul</hi> would have his <hi>Timothy</hi> (and ſo all others too in his Place and Heavenly Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) not to be like the dry and ſapleſs ſtumps of the grove, always at a ſtand; but like the more juicy, thriving Plants of the Garden; keeping not onely their a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ore ſpriteful verdure, but ſhooting forth too into ſome high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er meaſures of exemplary improvement and perfection:
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:63490:5"/> He would have all ſuch as are called to ſerve at the Altar, not only barely to keep their ſacred fire from going out, but to be exemplary too, in blowing it up into ſome higher, and hotter flames, than ever yet it had before; In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, like his moſt excellent ſelf, when he tells the Philip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pians, 3. <hi>Philip</hi> 13.1. I count not my ſelf to have apprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but this one thing I do, forgetting thoſe things which are behind, and reaching forth unto thoſe things which are before.</p>
            <p>The Text then, you ſee (My Reverend Brethren) ſeems to be nothing more than our Lure, or rather Alarm, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling us all to a greater meaſure and degree of Sacerdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal exemplarineſs and perfection; awakening us too, out of all that ſcandalous torpor and oſcitancy, out of all thoſe empty profeſſions and formalities, we are too too apt to allow our ſelves in, and to put our people off withal, in all our reſpective Duties and Services; for, you plainly ſee, St. <hi>Paul</hi> thinks it not enough for <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy</hi> to be a meerly ſpeculative, notional Divine, a great Caſuiſt, and Critick, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15. an excellent Tex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuary (or one mighty in the Scriptures, for ſo <hi>Timothy</hi> was) unleſs he prove a good Expoſitor too upon them, in his life: All theſe accompliſhments, indeed, he looks upon as very laudable and illuſtrious in their kind and place; but, unleſs this Gold be well grac't with the Ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mel, the Rubies, and precious Pearles of an excellent Spirit, a viſible Charity, Faith and Purity, 'twill never have that countenance, or acceptance that becomes an Ambaſſador of the moſt high God, nor yet that ſpark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling taking beauty that becomes a Jewel fixed in the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred boſom of the Church: Wherefore St. <hi>Paul</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſeth <hi>Timothy</hi> (and in him all of us) above all, to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove and preſent our ſelves upon the open ſtage of the world, as Examples of Believers in word, in converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in charity, in ſpirit, in faith, and in purity.</p>
            <p>The Text then; ſeems to exact and call for our ſtricter thoughts and reflections upon theſe four following Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars, it preſents us withal.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:63490:5"/>
            <p>The firſt is, the very great (but greatly neglected) Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Sacerdotal Exemplarineſs, indiſpenſably incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent upon all ſuch of us, eſpecially, who are prime Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, or yet, but inferior Officers of the Church, in theſe words,—<hi>But be; thou an example —Thou,</hi> eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, O <hi>Timothy,</hi> who art in a place of ſpecial truſt, and Eccleſiaſtical Authority.</p>
            <p>Secondly, We have a juſt Enumeration of all thoſe more choice and ſingular inſtances and particulars, wherein <hi>Timothy</hi> (and ſo, all others too, in his Sacerdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal ſacred circumſtances) ought, eſpecially, thus to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear and preſent themſelves, as eminent patterns and examples, and they are no more or leſs than ſix, but ſuch, as are ready to make us all bright, and victorious in the eyes of all our ſevereſt Adverſaries, <hi>viz.</hi> We muſt be examples of Believers in word, in converſation, in charity, in ſpirit, in faith, and in purity.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, We have the ſpecification of thoſe particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar perſons, to whom <hi>Timothy</hi> is thus oblig'd to be an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, and lively pattern, in all theſe heavenly perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and they are <hi>Believers;</hi> ſuch, it ſeems, as walk ſo ſtedfaſtly by faith, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.8. that they look not at the things which are ſeen, 11 <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. but confeſs rather that they are Pilgrims and Strangers on earth, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.5. Such, as have ſo given themſelves to the Lord, as that, 1 <hi>Phil.</hi> 21. to them, to live is Chriſt: Theſe are the perſons, before whom, St. <hi>Paul</hi> would have his <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy,</hi> to walk, as ſuch a burning and ſhining light, in all places, and in all his practiſes, as that they may, from thence, derive freſh ſtrength and encouragement to ſight the good fight, and to run the race that is ſet before them with joy, and faithfulneſs.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, We have a ſpecial motive impli'd, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forcing this ſo great a Duty of Sacerdotal Exemplarineſs, impoſ'd in theſe words—<hi>Let no man deſpiſe thy youth;</hi> —importing nothing more than this, That, if <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy</hi> made not himſelf thus an example of Believers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n word, in converſation and charity, in ſpirit, in faith, and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:63490:6"/> in purity, he went the ready way [eſpecially, being but a young man] to be made, himſelf, by others, an example of publick ſcorn, reproach, and infamy. And now, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving preſumed to give you this plain account of the words, and as plainly paraphraſed them too, for the better advantage of the more narrow vulgar capacities under me, I doubt not, but you all ſee <hi>your graver ſelves,</hi> not a little concerned in them; and my ſelf too unavoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably oblig'd, to ſtir up all your purer minds, by way of remembrance, of the</p>
            <p>Firſt, Remarkable in in the Text; and that is, <hi>The great Duty of Sacerdotal Exemplarineſs;</hi> Indeed a Duty never more needful from the creation, than in this our preſent age and generation; an age, that flyes at all Learning; an age, matchleſs and incomparable for know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; an age, that ſeems to be even ſurfeited with our Sermons, and now inquires and looks into nothing more, than the lives, the faults and defects of the Clergie.</p>
            <p>In my proſecution then, of this ſo important a point, I hope 'twill not appear either unſeaſonable or unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable if I endeavour an humble ſuggeſtion of what (I know) your more acute and piercing judgmnets, and better experience, hath already taught and told you all, concerning,</p>
            <p>Firſt, The great Influence and Efficacy, and then,</p>
            <p>Secondly, The great Obligation and Neceſſity of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplarineſs <hi>(on our parts, eſpicially)</hi> who are, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. the pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſt Ambaſſadors of the moſt high God.</p>
            <p>Suffer me then, a little, firſt to give you my preſent medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations (ſuch, poſſibly, as may, at leaſt awaken your own exacter conceptions) touching the too too much unobſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved influence and efficacy of Example; for, I am apt to fear, it's a great truth, many of us oftner mind <hi>others</hi> of, from our Pulpits, than mind ſeriouſly <hi>our ſelves,</hi> as we ſhould, when we are out of them, <hi>viz.</hi> That Exampl's more prevailing than Precept: But, he that will be at the pains ſeriouſly to conſider, how really lifeleſs the moſt
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:63490:6"/> perſwaſive language is, unleſs back't with a behaviour correſponding with it:</p>
            <p>He that will find but ſo much leaſure, as attentively to obſerve, how commonly ſucceſleſs, the moſt unwearied, importunities, [<hi>Si vis me ſlere,</hi> &amp;c.] for tears from others eyes are, unleſs our own be <hi>first</hi> Examples, themſelvs, in ſuch like dolorous effuſions, will ſoon conclude the victorious, and triumphant power of Example over that of the moſt flouriſht and Rhetoricated Precept: And, indeed, there is a natural inclination and propenſneſs in all men, to learn the <hi>Theory beſt,</hi> of ſuch, as they <hi>know,</hi> are beſt at the Practick; and the reaſon may be that of <hi>Seneca,</hi> in his ſixth Epiſtle to <hi>Ludilius,</hi> where he tells him, <hi>Homines plus oculis, quam auribus credant, That men give greater credit to their eyes, than their ears,</hi> to what they <hi>ſee in</hi> us, than what they <hi>hear from</hi> us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Valerius Corvinus</hi> therefore, ſet out with advantage, when, marching againſt his prepared enemy, he thus beſpeaks his own Army; <hi>Facta mea, non dicta vos Mill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, ſequi volo,</hi> &amp;c. Noble Sirs, let my <hi>Deeds</hi> be your conduct: words may prove but wind. Let then, <hi>Tertullus</hi> his tongue be ne're ſo well tipt with his ſilver perſwaſions, yet, if his practiſe give not life to his ſplendid expreſſions, and ſtrength to his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſtile, he goes the ready way, to make himſelf, not only <hi>derided,</hi> but <hi>ridiculous</hi> too, to all his more wary and watchful obſervers. Indeed, like them, <hi>Quis de virtute locuti,</hi> &amp;c. the Poet points at, ſo approbri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, for being ſcarce men, for manners and converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, whilſt they are vertues greateſt Patrons, in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence and expreſſion; in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> language, 1 <hi>Titus,</hi> 16. <hi>Such who profeſs they know God, but in their works deny him.</hi> Weak therefore, in compariſon, very feeble and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>effectual muſt needs be the perſwaſions of a flouriſhing Phariſee, who <hi>ſayes,</hi> but <hi>does</hi> not; who makes others <hi>loaded Porters,</hi> whilſt himſelf's but <hi>a lazy Preacher,</hi> and impoſer of the burden: This ſeem'd ſo great an abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity in the eyes of that Holy Father St. <hi>Bernard,</hi> that
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:63490:7"/> we read him, in one of his Epiſtles, checking it for a moſt praepoſterous practiſe; <hi>Pulcherrimus hic or do eſt, &amp; ſaluberrimus, ut onus, quod portandum imponis, tu por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes prior: Sermo quidem vivus &amp; efficax, Exemplar eſt operis; facile faciens ſuadibile quod dicitur, dum monſtras factibile quod ſuadetur. This is</hi> (ſayes he) the <hi>ſoundeſt,</hi> and moſt ſeemly Order and Method for men (eſpecially for the Miniſters of Chriſt) that they firſt bear Chriſts yoak <hi>themſelves,</hi> which they call upon others to bear; and then he adds, That, <hi>that Sermon</hi> is moſt like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to prove moſt quick and lively, that's fairly copied out, and tranſcrib'd in the Teachers life: And the truth is, there's nothing in the world makes our nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous hearers ſo much to ſhrink, as commonly they do, under all our preceptive Doctrines, as our own giving them too much reaſon to conclude them all impracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable, and impoſſible too (as it were) by the looſeneſs, and grand delinquencies, they often obſerve, in ſome of our lives.</p>
            <p>So great an Empire hath Example!</p>
            <p>Indeed, it muſt be a barren brain; a very cold and frozen invention, that's incapable of being thaw'd into a flow of affectionate expreſſions againſt ſin and Sinners (eſpecially, when the warm beams of ſome pleaſure, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt and reputation, beat upon it) I ſay, it muſt be an unpardonably dull ſoul; a very flegmatick Levite, that cannot make a ſhift (as the manner of ſome, is) ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, pathetically and vehemently to harangue, to <hi>ſpeech</hi> the common people, and amuſe them with an heap of Greek and Latine ſentences, and notions out of the Fathers and Schoolmen: A very Thief may diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe excellently againſt that very rapine and robbery, he makes the conſtant trade and task of his life; But now, <hi>that</hi> which renders a <hi>Paul,</hi> a <hi>Peter,</hi> a <hi>Timothy,</hi> and the like Ambaſſadors of the moſt high God, to be enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd with Trophy and Triumph, with the ſincereſt love and complacency in the hearts of their more wiſe and wary hearers, is, their making their <hi>lives</hi> fairly parallel
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:63490:7"/> with their language, and their own Exemplary diligence, in doing themſelves, what; with diligence, they incite and call upon others to do.</p>
            <p>We are then, as truly, as commonly told, That Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periours are the reputed Looking-glaſſes, by which the vulgar dreſs themſelves; and what they ſee in <hi>them,</hi> for the moſt part they'l quickly have as viſible in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, not caring much, if they periſh, ſo it be on <hi>ſuch</hi> credit, and with <hi>ſuch</hi> company.</p>
            <p>It was once thought a Queſtion, able to ſilence our Saviours greateſt Votaries, <hi>John,</hi> 7.48. <hi>Have any of the Rulers, and of the Phariſees believed in him?</hi> Imply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nothing more, than the great command of Exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary greatneſs: for had theſe Rulers, and aſſuming Phariſees (on whom the Jewiſh Nation, did then, ſo fondly dote) but really <hi>done</hi> more, and <hi>talked</hi> leſs; had theſe blazing ſtars but had a more friendly aſpect upon the <hi>Bethlehem</hi>-Babe, he had been, undoubtedly, imbrac't in thoſe very armes, we afterwards, find ſo deeply dy'd in his moſt ſacred blood.</p>
            <p>So great a power hath exemplary greatneſs!</p>
            <p>It's not for nothing then, that our Hiſtories inform us, how <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> being a learned Prince, himſelf, fil'd <hi>Rome</hi> with Schollars; hollow <hi>Tiberius</hi> with Diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blers; pious <hi>Constantine,</hi> with Chriſtians, and ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Julian,</hi> with Atheiſts, and Apoſtates. Such great lights, it ſeems, as theſe, like the glorious Sun, ſhed their influence irreſiſtably, either to the impairing, or better improving all their reſpective bodies, lying un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them; if they be fixed Stars, Saints eminent and conſpicuous for ſtrength and ſtedfaſtneſs in the faith, and the other heavenly perfections of the Text, ſuch glorious examples will have the like glorious iſſues and effects following them; they being like the pillar of cloud, <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpeaks of, <hi>when that went,</hi> Iſrael <hi>went too.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus, whilſt pious <hi>Joſhua</hi> lives, all this people look like ſo many leſſer lights, kindl'd at that more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>laſhing Lamp of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> Such a burning and ſhining light was
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:63490:8"/> 
               <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> that, it even <hi>ſunk</hi> the towring pride of <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod</hi> into a confeſſed Reverence, both for his perſon and Doctrine; and whilſt <hi>Theodoſius</hi> (the Emperour) will be exemplary in ſerving his God, his whole Court be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes the more Religious for it: whilſt they beheld their own ſullied faces in ſo <hi>true</hi> and <hi>clear</hi> a glaſs; their faults muſt needs be reflected with the greater ſhame and regret upon them themſelves: Others brighter vertues, ſhining forcibly upon our own faces, naturally colours our cheeks with the ſanguinary tincture of ſhame, or elſe they quicken our ſouls to an emulation of the ſame: It was therefore a commendable practice of <hi>that great Duke,</hi> who alwaies, before he went to his diet, had a baſon of water brought him, with the live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly picture of <hi>Cato</hi> Major, ſtampt in gold, at the bottom of it; it ſeems, the better to awaken his duller ſoul to the imitation of all thoſe illuſtrious vertues, that great example of the age he liv'd in was owner of: But now, on the contrary; if theſe Superiours prove but blazing Comets, we may then obſerve they do not ſo much pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, as actually procure moſt diſmal and diſaſterous effects, upon moſt of thoſe inferiour bodies they directly face and influence: Witneſs, that great inſtance of the Comick, when he brings in a timorous <hi>Vitioſo,</hi> encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raging himſelf to an unuſual villainy,
<q>Haec ego non faciam, quae <hi>Jupiter</hi> facit,</q> 
               <hi>ſayes he,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Shall I flinch to act <hi>that,</hi> that I ſee <hi>even Jupiter,</hi> act before my face: It ſeems, that very ſin he ſweats, (as 'twere) to think on, at firſt, now, grows more kindly and familiar, by the countenance he ſaw it had from his Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour: Great men's ſins, prove contagious to more than themſelves. And indeed, my little reading tells me, that the unſtable vulgar, in all the Regions of the world, have been ever carried away with the Religion of Authority: Thus, let <hi>Aaron,</hi> the Prieſt, make a mol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Calf, in the ſight of the people, and he ſhall have them Calfs, themſelves, or very children, in their ready compliance with Idolatry: Let but <hi>Corah</hi> firſt kindle the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:63490:8"/> fire (though a ſtrange one) and two hundred and fifty Captains will quickly bring ſticks to it, and all <hi>Iſrael</hi> too, will warm themſelves at it. If <hi>Peter</hi> once play the diſſembler, he ſhall quickly have a whole troop, as good at paint and palliation as himſelf, with a <hi>Barna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bas</hi> to boot: We read, <hi>Gala.</hi> 2.14. St. <hi>Paul</hi> taxing this <hi>Peter,</hi> for being thus a bad pattern.—<hi>Why com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelleſt thou the Gentiles, to live as do the Jews;</hi> but, how, did <hi>Peter</hi> compell the Gentiles to Judaize:<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Non docentis imperi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſantis Exempl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Hier. Ep. 11.</hi>
               </note> Not by any thing he <hi>preach't</hi> to them (ſaith a Father) but by his Example; It ſeems, <hi>Peter's</hi> Example, proves the peoples compul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; for, indeed, there is a kind of Compulſion in Example, though not violent, yet alluring, and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractive: Thus, let <hi>Eli's</hi> Sons appear ſmutty in the view of the people, and they ſhall not ſtay long for as black a train, as themſelves, to follow them; Indeed, like <hi>Jacob's</hi> ſheep; whilſt they fondly pore upon the ſpeck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Rods of Poplar, they ſoon multiply into a numerous iſſue, as ſtrangely ſpeckled, as their patterns.</p>
            <p>And now, my Brethren! muſt we all grant Example to be indu'd, (as we we have heard at large) with ſuch an attractive aſſimulating vertue? Muſt we aſcribe ſuch a boundleſs Empire and command to example, as that it makes the <hi>mightiest Monarch,</hi> as well as the meaneſt Subject, to ſtoop to it's Scepter? And ſhall not we, even we, who are God's profeſt Ambaſſadors, ſee our ſelves highly concern'd to imbrace it? eſpecially our Example being ſo ſure a ſubordinate means to make effectual that Embaſſie, which, otherwiſe, I fear, will ſeem (at leaſt, to ſome) but little more, than fabulous and nugatory? Suffer me then, to paſs from the great influence and efficacy, and humbly preſent you all with an account of the ſecond concern of the Text, being the great obligation and neceſſity of a Religious Exemplari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, on our parts eſpecially, who are all made ſo much a ſpectacle to Men and Angels, as indeed, we are, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring all our continuance upon the open ſtage of this world.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:63490:9"/>
            <p>In the general then; may not we, I ſay, eſpecially, of the Clergy, all confeſs, in this caſe of exemplary pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſing (as St. <hi>Paul</hi> did, of preaching the Goſpel, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.16. <hi>A neceſſity is laid upon us, and woe be to us, if we preach not the Goſpel in a</hi> laudable life, as well, as in an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligible language; Woe be to us (above all others) 2 <hi>Tit.</hi> 20. if we adorn not the Goſpel of God, our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, in all things! eſpecially, ſince I fear, that many of our lives are, and have been ſuch, as, were <hi>Luther</hi> now alive, he might well repeat his old complaint, <hi>viz. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecto aut hoc non est Evangelium, aut nos non fumus Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelici:</hi> That, truly, either it's not the Goſpel, which we preach, or elſe that we diſclaim the ſame Goſpel from being the copy, or conduct of our practiſe. But this Neceſſity, of our being thus exemplary, above others, will the more convincingly appear to us all, if we ſhall but go aſide, and ſometimes conſider with our ſelves, That there is, 1. The voice of Chriſt, our Maſter. 2. The voice of the Goſpel our Rule. 3. The voice of the Church, our Mother. 4. The voice of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, our Controller, and then, <hi>Vox populi</hi> too, the voice of the People (our moſt cenſurious obſervers) all very preſſing and importunate with us all, that we, even we, above all, would <hi>(eſpecially in the preſent age we live in)</hi> be more punctual and impartial Conformiſts to this great Canon, confirm'd by heaven's authority, <hi>viz. Be thou an Example of the Believers,</hi> &amp;c. Let us here, then attend a while to all theſe <hi>calls,</hi> and conſider all the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective urgencies imported in them all.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Then, there is the voice of Chriſt, our Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, very urgent in this matter: For, if Chriſts com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſheep muſt hear his voice, how much more, ought his Shepheards then, when he calls upon them, <hi>Math.</hi> 5. <hi>To do more then others do?</hi> telling them too, <hi>Their righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs must exceed the righteouſneſs of the Scribes and Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees:</hi> Again, if Chriſt's common ſheep muſt hear his voice, how much more his Shepheards then, when he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claims them (in the ſame breath) <hi>the lights of the world,</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:63490:9"/> and therefore looks, that <hi>their</hi> light ſhould ſo ſhine be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore men, that they may ſee <hi>their</hi> good works t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>their</hi> Charity, by way of eminency: It ſeems by all this, and much more, that might be ſuggeſted out of that fifth of <hi>Matthew,</hi> Chriſt expects the lights of the Sanctuary, ſhould be, above all others, conſpicuous and exempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: <hi>They</hi> muſt <hi>ſo</hi> ſhine, though <hi>others</hi> do not ſo: The light of the Star will not pleaſe, where the light of the Sun's expected: A ruſh candle's but a Toy, a very trifle and affront, where a flaming torch is to be tender'd: Far be it then from us ever to forget the no leſs juſt, than tart reflection of our Saviour upon the Prieſt and Levito. <hi>Luke,</hi> 10.31, 32. where, they are both taxt for being very ſhrubs for Charity, whilſt a meaner Samaritane ſeems a towring Cedar in the ſame.</p>
            <p>Chriſt, no doubr, look't for <hi>more</hi> Love from the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite, 3 for <hi>more</hi> Pity from the Prieſt towards that diſtreſſed Traveller, than from any other Paſſenger<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> If a Samaritane can beſtow but a ſingle ſigh upon a poor bleeding Brother, he expects the Tribute of Tears from the other: But ſuppoſe the Prieſts caſe be really that of St <hi>Peter,</hi> 3 <hi>Acts</hi> 6. That ſilver and gold he hath none, yet he is bound to give an example of giving ſuch as he hath: If he cannot ſhew he hath bags, yet he is bound to ſhew he hath bowels; yea, what he wants in the one, he's oblig'd to double in the other: If <hi>Moſes</hi> ſtoop ſo low, as to ſit at the table with the Father leſs and the Widow, methinks it will not ill become <hi>Aaron</hi> to lie at their Feet, for their Good; We read, <hi>John</hi> 13. that our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, having firſt waſh't his Diſciples feet, preſently preſcribes a law for them to do the like, ver. 15. <hi>I have given you an example</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>that you ſhould do as I have done to you.</hi> But,</p>
            <p>Secondly, There is the voice of the Goſpel, (our Rule) very preſſing too, in this particular: You know in the general, it calls upon all, (but eſpecially upon us, that preach it) 2 <hi>Titus</hi> 12. <hi>That we we live ſoberly, righteouſly, and godly in this preſent world:</hi> Indeed, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:63490:10"/> layes a neceſſity upon all, (but upon us, the diſpenſers of it) above all, 1 Peter 2.12. <hi>to have our converſation ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, among the Gentiles, that whereas they ſpeak againſt us, as evil-doers, they may, by our good works, which they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, glorifie Gid in the day of viſitation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The truth is, if we, who preach <hi>the Goſpel,</hi> do not adorn and make it bright and glorious in the eyes of the prophaner part of the world; by ſuch an holy conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, as it <hi>eſpecially</hi> calls for <hi>from us, and it,</hi> as really deſerves <hi>from all, this</hi> muſt needs be the black ſequel of it, That we ſhall (to our own greater infamy and confuſion) be found ſuch, who baſely ſtrangled that, we pretended to ſtrengthen; and appear very murde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers of that friend, we once made the world believe in our Pulpits, we all valued above our lives and deareſt poſſeſſions.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, There is the voice of the Church (our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Mother) very importunate too, in this matter; Concluding it, <hi>indeed,</hi> as well ſhe may, the actual pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of her juſt honour and reputation, by ſo many of her profeſſed ſons, as are not thus examples of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, in life and converſation: It were to diſparage ſo Learned an Aſſembly, as is here, for ſo mean an Orator, as my ſelf, to diſplay before you the incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable Excellencies of this our aged Mother, the Church of <hi>England.</hi> This is done already, eſpecially of late, by ſo many and matchleſs Pens, that it makes it unqueſtionably ſuperfluous form, were I as able, as willing, to attempt it from the Pulpit: But this, I may, and muſt ſay,—</p>
            <p>That She remains to this day (not withſtanding all the malitious imputations and aſperſions of the black mouth'd Jeſuit, and all his diſguiſed agents) a Mother, tranſcendent for an exemplary purity, and many other graceful perfections: Her reſpective Laws and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions (though it hath pleaſ'd ſome certain ſelfiſh, prejudicate, and vain Opiniators of the age, we live in, to vilifie and undervalue <hi>her</hi> and <hi>them</hi>) are yet, known
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:63490:10"/> to perſons; if not <hi>more,</hi> yet altogether as pious and learned as themſelves, to be ſuch, as drive at nothing more, than to diſpoſe all her ſons (but eſpecially, thoſe that ſerve at the altar) to a ſuperlative degree of holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs towards God, and, 2 <hi>Tit.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>in all things to ſhew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves patterns of good works to men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It muſt be confeſt, indeed, her ſons are not all alike: It's poſſible, ſome there are, to be found of St <hi>Bernard's</hi> black brood, whom he brands, for being<note n="(a)" place="margin">De honeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta Cleri, &amp; atatis a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum.</note> blots of their profeſſion, the very ſcorn, and ſcars of the age, they live in; And it may be too, St. <hi>Augu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tin</hi> his complaint may not be altogether unjuſt, <hi>viz.</hi> That<note n="(b)" place="margin">Adhuc Arca Corvum &amp; co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Continet <hi>Ang. 145.</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt.</note> the clean and unclean birds, the Dove and the Raven, are, to this day, in the Ark, and Church of God: Like the holy Families of the Patriarchs, ſo it is with many Churches, they have their impurer mixtures; Thus, in <hi>Adams</hi> Family, there was holy <hi>Abel,</hi> and wicked <hi>Cain, Noah's,</hi> Family, there was bleſſed <hi>Shem</hi> and curſed <hi>Ham,</hi> In <hi>Abraham's</hi> Family, there was devout <hi>Iſaac,</hi> and ungodly <hi>Iſhmael;</hi> in <hi>Iſaac's</hi> Family, there was reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious <hi>Jacob</hi> and prophane <hi>Eſau;</hi> yea, in Chriſt's own Family there was a <hi>Judas,</hi> a ſon of perdition: And thus, if the Church of <hi>England</hi> (our Mother) may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of her mixtures; of ſome <hi>Reubens,</hi> for being as unſtable as water, of ſome <hi>Simeon's</hi> and <hi>Levi's</hi> too, <hi>for having the inſtruments of cruelty in their habitations;</hi> yet, all theſe, and all ſuch, ſhe carefully conſignes to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, never approves of; <hi>Theſe,</hi> I ſay, (with <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> there) ſhe pathetically diſclaims, <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.6. <hi>O my ſoul! come not thou into their ſecret, unto their aſſembly, mine honour! be not thou united.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And is it not pity? yea, is it not a great ſhame for any of us (the profeſſed ſons of ſuch a Mother) by our inexemplary and unſuitable, lives, to ſcandalize her pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer Doctrine, and by a looſe add licentious carriage, to bring an ill report upon her diſcipline?</p>
            <p>I would it were better conſidered by us all, how much it gratifies the many Papal Spies crept into our
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:63490:11"/> 
               <hi>Canaan,</hi> when they hear of the high animoſities and heart-burnings, the cenſorious language, and the bitter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vectives of Brother againſt Brother, even in the boſom of this their Mother!</p>
            <p>I could heartily wiſh, I ſay, it were taken into all our moſt retired thoughts, how much it hardens and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms the factious and ſchiſmatical, when they obſerve the ſoft and pacifique voice of this our Mother, ſo little minded by her own Sons.</p>
            <p>It was a tart reprehenſion therefore (but how true, and deſervedly given, I know not) which a Romaniſt, I am told, gave to one of us, as of old was ſaid of the Monk,
<q>
                  <l>Tu praeter amictum,</l>
                  <l>Nil aliud verae religionis habes.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>I am loath to Engliſh it, for I come not hither to fling dirt, or play the Satyriſt; but I fear, too too many of us much more mind the formality of our habits, than the real honeſty of our hearts; thinking it enough to wear our Mother the (Churches Livery) not concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our ſelves whether we do her either ſervice or cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit by our lives.</p>
            <p>But let not, oh! let not this our Mother complain of us, as <hi>Zion</hi> once, <hi>Lament.</hi> 4.13, 14. <hi>How is the gold become dim! how is the most fine gold changed! For the ſins of my Prophets, and the iniquity of my Prieſts, the people have wandred as blind men in the ſtreets.</hi> But,</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Methinks, I now hear St. <hi>Peter's</hi> Cock crowing; I mean the voice of conſcience (our imparti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al controller) calling on us too, in this concern, and telling, <hi>even the beſt of us,</hi> were we all well weighed in the ballance of the ſanctuary, we ſhould be found too light in this great Duty of being thus Exemplary,—ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of us, ſeeming to be very <hi>Angels</hi> in the <hi>Doctrine,</hi> whilſt I fear, ſcarce <hi>men,</hi> in the <hi>uſe</hi> and Application, we make our ſelves, of our Sermons.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:63490:11"/>
            <p>I have heard, ſome where, That <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Macedon</hi> diſplac't a Judge becauſe he colour'd his beard; he was jealous, it ſeems, he might colour a Cauſe too: I know not how true that was, but I think it an unqueſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onable aſſertion, that, many, of our Coat, have their Conſciences telling them, they deſerve the ſame cenſure and ſeverity, not more for colouring their <hi>own</hi> Sermons, than <hi>others</hi> ſins, making thereby their ſacred Calling more to ſerve themſelves, than endeavouring <hi>themſelves,</hi> really to ſerve their Calling: I come not hither to accuſe or diſcourage any!</p>
            <p>But tell me, My Brethren! think you not, that there are ſome amongſt us (though I hope none here) whoſe Conſciences may be their doleful accuſers, for being their people's dangerous deluders? Tell me, I ſay, are there not thoſe to be found in the Nation, whoſe own Conſciences ring them many a ſad peal, out of the hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the world, for making <hi>Aaron</hi>'s bells to go ſo ill, inſomuch, that they have now liv'd to hear their own knells gone, for being (as I may ſay) quite dead and gone in the hearts of the people.</p>
            <p>Others, there are too, I doubt not, but you have heard of, who have made ſo ill uſe of the keys of the Church, that it had been much better for both, had they quietly laid them under the door, and then, withdrawn out of ſight and hearing: For, the open diſcovery, and detection of ſome of their ill and unwarrantable practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes hath not only made the guilty to be almoſt irreco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verably deſpiſ'd, but the innocent too, to be the more ſuſpected.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pardon, great God! theſe ſins of thy ſervants!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, My Brethren! ſince thus it is; and, it may be, much worſe too, with many of our <hi>weaker Brethren;</hi> ſince, I ſay, <hi>even the beſt of us,</hi> have not been ſo good examples, as we might have been; and with <hi>Auſtin,</hi> have reaſon to beſpeak the Majeſty of heaven, as he, <hi>Libera me Domine a peccatis meis alienis;</hi> From my other men's ſins; or, thoſe, I have, by my ill example tempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:63490:12"/> others too, Good Lord! deliver me! is not then, the voice of our Conſcience <hi>within,</hi> the more preſſing and importunate, for our being <hi>the more lively examples of Believers to thoſe, that are without?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh then! Let us not turn the deaf ear to this Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, leaſt the voice of it, which would be our friendly Monitor, in time prove our fatal, fearful Tormentor, when we are lanch't forth into the boundleſs ocean of Eternity!</p>
            <p>Fifthly, I am come now to the voice or Monitor, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>vox Populi,</hi> the voice of the people; a voice, <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed,</hi> in <hi>many</hi> caſes, not valuable, <hi>in this;</hi> I think, very conſiderable.</p>
            <p>Now, if we ſhall but ſit down and liſten a while to the declamatory language of ſome (and thoſe too, it may be, not ſo contemptible as we are apt to conclude them) I cannot but think all thoſe nails, drove in alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, will be the better clinch't in your ſpirits, e're we part.</p>
            <p>Indeed, time was, when the world had a better opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of us, than, I fear, <hi>now,</hi> it hath. Time hath been, when the world hath counted us worthy of double <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,</hi> as well as double <hi>Honour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay, we all read, that the very Heathen had an high eſteem for their Idol-prieſts: <hi>Plato</hi> tells us, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; There was ſtill a Reverence ſhew'd the Prieſt, and that, not in <hi>this,</hi> or <hi>that</hi> particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Nation, but, <hi>in Gentibus omnibus,</hi> &amp;c. (ſaith <hi>Figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi>) There is no Nation under heaven (ſayes he) where their Prieſts are not had in honour: He tells us too, that neglect and diſreſpect to the Prieſt, was a ſin, <hi>Viti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um Judaeis peculiare,</hi> peculiar to the Jews only. I have been told the people of <hi>England</hi> once ſaid of us, as I have read the old <hi>Caldees</hi> did of their Prieſts, <hi>viz. Homo quidam ex Judaeis venit Sacerdos, neutiquam decipiet nos. There's a Prieſt come to Town, he, we are ſure, will not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive us.</hi> But, alas! my Brethren! how many of us may complain that this our honeſty is turned into Gall:
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:63490:12"/> That this ſofter voice of our people, is turned into dreadful claps of thunder, in many of our Pariſhes. For indeed, he muſt needs be very thick of hearing, that cannot hear <hi>Rabſhekah</hi> railing againſt the Epiſcopal Robe; He muſt, I ſay, wink very hard, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> cannot ſee <hi>Hymeneus</hi> and <hi>Philetus, Alexander</hi> and <hi>Demetrius,</hi> contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving miſchief: You cannot be ignorant, how theſe Iron-moles, daily deface our Lawns and Surpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; you cannot but know, how theſe Mothes have fretted our Caſſocks and Girdles, with all the other de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent garments of our Mothers appointing.</p>
            <p>I need not tell you too, how, for the better impair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our intereſt in the hearts of the people, many of our daring Adverſaries have maliciouſly branded us; ſometimes, calling us, <hi>the Black Guard, The Leaches of the Land, Priests of</hi> Belial, <hi>The uſeleſs Tribe, Lazy Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites,</hi> and the like; confirming us (who hear and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider all this) in nothing more, than that they would quickly make us objects of their mercileſs rage and ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance, were it not for the life-guard of Royal pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence acted by a gracious and over-ruling Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</p>
            <p>Now, My Brethren! if theſe ſharp Razors ſhave <hi>Aaron</hi>'s beard ſo cloſe, what may we (the meaner ſervants of the Altar) look for, but, that they would ſoon ſlip into our Throats? Making us, as it were, miſerable ſacrifices at thoſe very Altars, where, we are devoted ſervants: And can we ſee all theſe acts of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity and Hoſtility, and not conclude it high time for us all to put on the whole armour <hi>of God,</hi> and reſolve to live more piouſly and exemplarily in the eye and obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation <hi>of men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Certainly, Sirs! 'tis high time for <hi>Sampſon</hi> then, to look about him, when the Philiſtines are upon him!</p>
            <p>And thus; 'tis high time for <hi>Timothy</hi> too, to become an example of Believers in word, in converſation and charity, when he is ready to be voted down by the people for an example of their diſpleaſure, ſcorn and fury.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:63490:13"/>
            <p>And now, for the timely prevention of this ſo ſore an evil, which I have ſeen under the Sun, I ſhall humbly crave your further attention to one voice (more importunate, if poſſible; than all the reſt) with us all, and that is, in the,</p>
            <p>Sixth, and <hi>Ult.</hi> place, <hi>The loud voice of our own moſt ſacred calling and profeſſion,</hi> which, I fear, meets not with the half of that Reverence and regard from us, we owe it, <hi>as men;</hi> but infinitely leſs more, <hi>as ſuch,</hi> who have, with ſo much ſeriouſneſs and ſolemnity taken up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us, to diſcharge all the reſpective duties of it.</p>
            <p>I am not ſo vain as to think I can, nor dare I pretend to offer any thing exactly anſwerable and commenſurate, either to the heights of our callings dignity, and deſerts, or the parts and expectations of ſo judicious an Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, as is here, this day.</p>
            <p>But, ſince your very great Charity hath been already experienc't by me, upon a like occaſion; and ſince the meaneſt Prieſt too, may bring without offence a Cole to that very Altar, where, the Greater <hi>Aaron</hi> ſerves, himſelf; and ſince, but a ſilly Cock, may be ſerviceable for the awakening of no leſs a Saint than an inſpired <hi>Peter,</hi> I ſhall preſume the more, upon the ſuggeſtion of ſome few, of the moſt important ond weighty conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, <hi>reſpecting this great Duty, of an exemplary con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation,</hi> from the voice of that high and holy Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of our own, (you are all, I doubt not, ſo well skil'd in, and ſo very great Maſters of, already.)</p>
            <p>Suffer me then, to put you in remembrance, That, 'tis a Calling, of whoſe very Eſſence and vital Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution it is, to bind the Owners of it, not only to their good behaviour, but, to be eminent examples too, of Believers, in all godlineſs and honeſty: It obligeth us, above all, that being Lights and Leaders to others, we ſhould all ſo walk in the world, that others may ſee our good works, as well as hear our good words: Like St. <hi>Baſil,</hi> of whom it was ſaid, That he look't up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on himſelf as eminently bound by his Calling not
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:63490:13"/> more to<note n="(*)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> ſpeak what was to be done, than to do what he ſpake; profeſſing (it ſeems) his bounden duty, not only to order his preaching aright <hi>in the ears,</hi> but his converſation too, <hi>in the eyes</hi> of the people.</p>
            <p>It's a Notion of the Naturaliſt, <hi>Quanto purius &amp; Coelo vicinius elementum, tanto magis obſequitur motui Coeli.</hi> That the purer and nearer, any Element is to the heavens above, the greater yieldableneſs, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance it alwaies manifeſts to all their reſpective mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. How <hi>heavenly</hi> then, ſhould we be, who are all the profeſt Ambaſſadors of <hi>heaven!</hi> whoſe proper ſphere, whoſe ſpecial office and imployment, ſtands in ſo near a dependance and vicinity to this place, of ſo pure and ſpotleſs a nature and ſociety!</p>
            <p>It's an excellent pen, therefore, which tells us, That want of leiſure and breeding; want of knowledge and ſtudy; blind zeal; courſe company, ſecular worldly affairs, and leſs obligation, may <hi>a tanto,</hi> and in part, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe many perſons; but 'tis impoſſible (ſayes my Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor) for a Miniſter of the Goſpel, to be tolerably diſhoneſt.</p>
            <p>The caſe is our own; ſo much being given to us, the more's expected from us; and hence (no doubt) it was, That the ſin of the Prieſt, coſt as much ſacrifice, as the ſin of the whole people: 'Twas a meditation worthy the perſon that firſt ſuggeſted it, when he tells us, That <hi>our calling,</hi> as 'tis moſt Eminent, ſo 'tis moſt ey'd, and worſt cenſur'd: If an Apoſtle rub an ear of Corn <hi>upon the Sabbath day, 'tis breaking the day: The people's motes, are accounted the Prieſt's beams; and anothers indifferency, is my Evil; ſome things being expedient, in reſpect of the</hi> man, <hi>which are really ſcandalous and inexcuſable, in reſpect of the Coat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am not ignorant, that many of us (impatient of the Sacerdotal Yoke) line it with a ſilken invention, ſmooth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over the ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ter, and excuſing their own inexcuſable vanities; With the Rhetorical varniſh, of telling their people, That they are fleſh and blood<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> men of like
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:63490:14"/> failings and infirmities with others; whom they teach, when (God knows) many of them need not tell their people ſo, ſince they know it but too well already: But then, others, there are, who, that their poor ſcandaliz'd prejudic't patients may ſwallow down all their ill prepared preſcriptions, the better; they <hi>ſmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly</hi> tell them, ſometimes, That the Gold's never the worſe for coming from a ſullied hand: The good Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Elijah</hi> refuſed not his breakfaſt, becauſe brought to him by a black Raven; What? (ſay they) if the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificer be unclean, is the offering ſo too? Was the Ark (the glory of <hi>Iſrael</hi>) e're the worſe, for coming from the foul fingers of the Philiſtines? <hi>Sampſon</hi> made much of his honey, although it came from a ſtenchy putri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fi'd Lion: But alas! My Brethren! theſe Sirengers are too foul themſelves, to cleanſe the mouths of the people, being furr'd and foul'd ſo much, as they are, through all thoſe groſs conceptions and intemperate ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, they often breath forth againſt ſuch ſulli'd, and diſobedient Sons of the Church.</p>
            <p>The people knew well enough, that all theſe preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and excuſes, (with many more, they have ſometimes put upon them) though they'l paſs for colourable Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torick, yet never for ſolid reaſon; eſpecially, ſince our Hearers are, moſt of them, ſenſible already, that they can as well tell ſuch looſe and ſcandalous Teachers, from as good Scripture and Reaſon too, <hi>Exod.</hi> 37.23. That the very ſnuffers of the Sanctuary (made to top others) were to be of pure Gold; And they read, <hi>Levit.</hi> 21.17, 18. That no perſon, having any blemiſh, was to offer the oblation of the Lord; and our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, himſelf, tells thoſe, that are to pull the mote out of their Brothers eye, they had need firſt to caſt out the beam that is in their own. I find it therefore, obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by a learned perſon, out of <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> very aptly for this purpoſe, when he tells us <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. That a Phyſitian had need to be a perſon alwaies in good plight, of a good colour and complexion him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf;
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:63490:14"/> otherwiſe the Patient will be ready to bid the Phyſitian heal himſelf firſt; and having, through his ill looks, a prejudice againſt his phyſick, his fancy will greatly hinder its efficacy: the applications eaſie. We read, <hi>Math.</hi> 7. that Chriſt taught his Diſciples, <hi>as one, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving authority, and not as the Scribes:</hi> And thus (no doubt) if ever we would preach to purpoſe, we muſt be followers of him; Labouring after the ſame mind, and the ſame manners too, which were ſo viſible and conſpicuous in his own moſt excellent perſon; that we may, with a like ingenuous confidence, appeal to our converſation, as did he, for his better reception, <hi>John</hi> 10.28. (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>the works which I do, they testifie of me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>This</hi> is that, which (above all our Comminations, Excommunications, and other ſeverer methods) will make us to exhort, and rebuke with authority, and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This</hi> is that, which will convey ſuch a might, and ſwaying Majeſty into all our Prayers and Sermons, as muſt needs conquer our diſcompoſed, and unruly people into a better, and more kindly compliances; yea, this is that, which will give life and ſpirits to our Liturgy; and make our Common Prayer, to come with an <hi>extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary</hi> power upon the hearts of the people; making <hi>that</hi> truly amiable and venerable, which (through the manifeſt impiety of ſome perſons) appears to ſome people, the more deſpicable: And, indeed, to hear a Prieſt upon the Lords Day, reading the holy prayers of the Church punctually, and without partiality, with a taking tone, with his eyes and hands lifted up with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence to heaven, and with all other poſtures and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of a devout Soul, in the eyes of the people, and yet, for thoſe very eyes to be undenyable weekly witneſſes of the Petitioners repeated Impieties, it muſt needs <hi>ſomething leſſen,</hi> if not altogether ſtiffle and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſh, as the devotion of the people; ſo too, the power and efficacy of the prayers, themſelves, upon them.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:63490:15"/>
            <p>I leave it for all ſuch vain Votaries to conſider 'twixt God and their own Conſciences, whether they appear not (if I may ſo ſay) rather devoutly impudent, than really pious and devout in the eyes of their more judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and conſidering Hearers: I ſhall leave it (I ſay) with ſuch perſons to conſider too, whether they are not a very great, (if not the only cauſe) why our Liturgy (they pretend ſo much to love, and reverence) having now ſerved <hi>England</hi> (as <hi>Jacob</hi> did <hi>Laban</hi>) one ſeven years more, and upward, yet, at laſt, it's put off but with blear-ey'd <hi>Leah,</hi> few looking ſo right upon it, as otherwiſe, probably they would do.</p>
            <p>I have once met with an old anonymous Greek Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, who tells his Reader, That if any one were to be choſen to pray for the people, he had need to be a very pious vertuous perſon himſelf; becauſe (ſayes he)<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> the God's would take more heed to ſuch a man's prayers. But; it's the known aſſertion of a far better man, than he (and I heartily wiſh it were more ſeriouſly thought on) <hi>Pſal.</hi> 66.18. <hi>That if I regard iniquity in my heart, the Lord will not hear me:</hi> And I think, this was the worm that lay at the root of the Phariſees long pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. Oh! <hi>(let it never lie at ours!) that they ſecretly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured widows houſes;</hi> Though they had the prayers of Saints, yet, it ſeems, they had the drifts and deſigns of devouring Devils. No wonder then, if ſuch ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cants have ſo little regard from God, and ſo much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach and controll from men. Guilt, you know, is that which quells the courage of the bold, that tyes the tongue of the eloquent, and that makes greatneſs it ſelf to ſneak, like <hi>Judas,</hi> and behave it ſelf but poorly in the eyes of the people.</p>
            <p>The ſenſe therefore, and apprehenſion, which St <hi>Paul</hi> had of the ill conſequence to the people, of an ill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience in the Preacher, ſeems to put him into a holy paſſion againſt the guilty, 2 <hi>Rom.</hi> 21. <hi>Thou that teacheſt another, teacheſt thou not thy ſelf? Thou that preacheſt a man ſhould not ſteal, doſt thou ſteal?</hi> You know too,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:63490:15"/>
'twas the ſenſe of the of a meer Ethnick,—<hi>Turpe eſt doctors, &amp;c,</hi> And, indeed, who can (as a moſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>xcel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Modern, pen, hath expreſt it, ready to my hand) with patience hear an inceſtuous <hi>Herod,</hi> preaching up Chaſtity? a <hi>Judas,</hi> zealouſly condemning covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; an hollow-hearted <hi>Phariſee</hi> reproving hypocriſie; or a greedy-ſtuft Glutton (who can make his belly his God) perſwading his people affectionatly to faſting even with the Quails in his mouth; Every word muſt needs recoil upon the Preacher with diſgrace and infamy, giving new Teeth, to that old taunt and ſarcaſme, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Phyſitian, heal thy ſelf.</hi> That plain, but pithy paſſage therefore, of the Father, ſeems to ſuit my purpoſe here. <hi>Non eſt ſpecioſa laus, in ore peccatoris;</hi> It ill becomes Leapers (ſayes he) to hand the purer bread of life to others: And this, poſſibly might be one reaſon, why Chriſt himſelf, <hi>Mark,</hi> 1.25. rebuked the unclean ſpirit, and commanded him to hold his peace, <hi>even then,</hi> when he proclaim'd him to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the holy one of God:</hi> And I am told one reaſon why St <hi>Paul (with his holy Companions)</hi> being vexed with the praiſe of the Pythoniſt (<hi>Acts</hi> 16,) crying out, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Theſe men are the Servants of the most high God,</hi> even then, commanded the ſpirit to come forth of her,—<hi>Quaſi nolens ſanctus ab immundo ore com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendari:</hi> As though (as <hi>Tertullian</hi> tells us) he abhor'd praiſe coming from ſo impure a perſon: And the truth is (as <hi>Epictetus</hi> hath it <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Good things loſe much of their grace, good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and flavour, when they are not done by good men, as well as after a good manner: Hence, <hi>Tacitus</hi> informs us of <hi>Tiberius</hi> and <hi>Galba,</hi> as being men, though well ſpoken; perſons, of excellent pretences and expreſſions, yet, diſtaſted by the people; <hi>Non enim ad hanc for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>am catera erant:</hi> Becauſe their <hi>works,</hi> kept not touch with their <hi>words.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>It ſeems, they trod too much inward;</hi> looking ſecretly upon themſelves, what e're they pretended for the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:63490:16"/> peoples profit, to others: You have all read (I doubt not) as well as my meaner ſelf; That it was <hi>Pythagoras</hi> his confirming his excellent precepts with his own perſonal practice of them himſelf; it was, I ſay, that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the agreement of his life, with his lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, that made all <hi>Italy</hi> become <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; all the Country his School, and all, that ever heard him, his reſolved Diſciples.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lactantius</hi> therefore, taught to purpoſe the preachers of his dayes, when he tells them, <hi>Oportet Concionatorem non ſolum virtutis doctorem ſe praebere ſed &amp; ducem:</hi> That, it's the high concern of all Preachers, not only to ſhew themſelves good Teachers in the Pulpit, but they are as well to ſhew themſelves as good Leaders too, out of it: Like the Star, which led the Wiſe men unto Chriſt; and the Pillar of Fire, which led the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> unto <hi>Canaan;</hi> they did not <hi>only ſhine,</hi> but <hi>go before</hi> them too.</p>
            <p>It's not enough then, for us, <hi>to fall</hi> in with the truth, (as the manner of many is to do) <hi>and barely to hold the myſtery of faith,</hi> but we muſt do it in a pure Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence:</p>
            <p>The learned <hi>Aretius,</hi> therefore (gloſſing upon that, aptly ſuggeſts; <hi>Non ſolum peritus in religione, ſed &amp; Gastus in moribus:</hi> That a Miniſter ſhould not only be <hi>skilful</hi> in his Profeſſion, but very careful too, of his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation: He is oblig'd (above all others) to grace his Calling and Profeſſion, with a gracious Life and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation; For, <hi>that,</hi> will never have the credit of being pure and undefiled, till we, who diſpenſe i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, keep our ſelves more pure and unſpotted from the world. If then, we do not this, We, above all, affront our God, and diſhonour our King, We, above all, ſtain our Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſtrangle our Conſciences: and then too, We, above all, do crucifie (as much as in us lies) the Biſhop of our Souls, as well as the Biſhop of the Dioceſs; and after all, whilſt we preach to others, may well ſuſpect to prove <hi>but caſt awaies our ſelves:</hi> Oh then! let not this
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:63490:16"/> be the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or infamous Character <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> our ſacred Order, <hi>That we are famous Preachers, but in famous Livers.</hi> That we are in holy Orders, but ſtill in the gall of bitterneſs, and in the bends of iniquity: But, let us all rather often ſeriouſly conſider with our ſelves, to what circumſpection; to what ſtrictneſs and innocency of Converſation; to what Sanctity, <hi>and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> then worldly induſtry,</hi> our ſacred Office and Profeſſion calls us all unto; bearing alwaies ſteadily upon our hearts, what St. <hi>Paul</hi> has ſet ſo punctually before our eyes, 1 <hi>Tim</hi> 4.16. <hi>Take heed into thy ſelf, and unto thy Doctrine, continue in it, for in doing this, thou ſhalt both ſave thy ſelf, and them that hear thee.</hi> But here, now, I would not all this while be miſtaken, by ſuch as are not of my own Calling and Profeſſion; as if my Maſters Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion were ſo confin'd to thoſe of my own Coat, as that it reacht not others too, of another calling.</p>
            <p>No, I am to charge your all, by all that's dear unto you, <hi>even as you are Christians;</hi> that you alſo <hi>be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of Believers, in Word, in Converſation, in Charity, in Spirit, in Faith, in Purity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If we, who are your poor devoted Servants, preach up Charity and Purity to you, in our Pulpits, and then, ſincerely endeavour a more lively expreſſion and repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation of them in our Practiſes, and you, in the mean time, let all get no further then the eyes and ears, what, I pray, is this, but to make your own Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation the greater? What our Saviour then, ſaid to ſome others, we may ſay to you, <hi>John</hi> 17.22. <hi>If we had not come and ſpoken unto you, you had not had ſin; but now, you have no cloak for your ſin.</hi> Think not then, that God fends you ſuch ſhining lights, for to ſport and play withal, but rather to improve them.</p>
            <p>Think not, that God ſends you ſuch burning lights too, only to make you a little luke warm; but rather, that your little ſpark of grace, that your ſmoaking Flax, may, by them; become an enlarged Flame. Think not, that the high and holy God ſends his Ambaſſadors
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:63490:17"/> for you to laugh at, but to make your mourn penitently, for thoſe very ſins, which, otherwiſe, will ſend you mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning perplexedly into infernal flames.</p>
            <p>Think not then, That God ſends his ſilver Trumpets (ſounding daily in your ears) only to lull and lay you aſleep, but rather to rouſe and awaken your duller Souls from the ſleep of ſin, unto ſome higher meaſures and degrees of of activeneſs for God, and the ſaving of your immortal Souls. Oh, Sirs! beware of barren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and ſterility, after ſo much labour beſtowed upon you. You know the fate of the fruitleſs Figtree. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware then, I ſay, after all our weeping over you, like ſome Cloth, you ſhrink not in the wetting: Believe me, this will ſend many of us away with Tears in our Eyes to our Graves, but your ſelves, I fear, with ſtings in your Conſciences: Oh then! let us all (but Officers eſpecially belonging to the Church) drive at that emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency of Holineſs and Purity, that becomes perſons in ſuch places of Eccleſiaſtical Authority: Let not your Courts be called Spiritual, whilſt their Officers appear but Carnal: Let not your Conſciences tell you at death, you had once an opportunity to make thoſe more exemplary by your power, whom, we, of the Clergy, could not make ſo, by our preaching; yet, you either cowardly or corruptly conniv'd at all their obſtinacies, and wilful affronts offer'd to the Church: The Jews, I have read, had their <hi>Terriculamenta Corvorum;</hi> Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain gaſtly formidable Pictures, or Images, ſet by their Altars to fright away offenſive birds; but the learned <hi>Selden</hi> tells us of a complaint of a later Rabbin, That when the birds ſaw theſe Images or Pictures did them no harm, they would commonly ſteal fleſh away from the Altars, and ſit upon their heads to eat, and dung on them, when they had done, The moral is eaſie and familiar: How happy then were it for the Church, and the whole Nation too, were all their reſpective Officers better Examples of Believers <hi>themſelves,</hi> in Word, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation and Charity; and in a diſcreet execution of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:63490:17"/> the Laws; without cowardice, or corrupt partiality<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Then, I am apt to think we ſhould not have <hi>ſome</hi> of our Church-wardens ſo unmindful of their Oaths, and others, ſo unfaithful to their promiſes, as, I fear, we have ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, in our Pariſhes: You are all, by your places and offices obliged to ſerve the Church, either by the Oath, you have taken, or the promiſe, you have made; Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks then, you ſhould ſee your ſelves the more obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to execute your authority, without the leaſt wilſul connivance or partiality: But, alaſs! how frequent, and familiar is it amongſt many of you, to preſent only ſome poor impotent cleeted Delver, but paſs by the more reſponſible luxurious <hi>Dives!</hi> how common, I ſay, is it, with many of you to preſent your poorer Neighbors, whilſt you ſuffer your brutiſh Betters to make their Chambers, their only Churches upon the Lords day, and rhe Alehouſe or Tavern, the chiefeſt pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of reſort all the week after. Have not many of you a ſcandalous ſort of Superiours (ſuch as they be) about you, who propagate Atheiſm, Irreligion, and open pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneſs in your Pariſhes, by their daring Oaths, Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings and new coyn'd execrations, with many other un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian practiſes?</p>
            <p>Oh! then, wrong not the Church, the Nation, and your own Conſciences, by being ſuch timerous reſpecters, of perſons: Diſgrace not your papers of Preſentments, with wrapping up in them only the ſhreds and rags of your Pariſh, ſince you may ſo eaſily find Silks and Sat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tins enough to ſupply them; and indeed, were the ſpots and ſtains better rub'd out of <hi>theſe,</hi> I cannot but think, there would be more of the beauty of holineſs amongſt the reſt of your meaner Inhabitants; Would you be ſo piouſly couragious, as to top the luxuriant branches of theſe taller Cedars, you would quickly find the courſer Shrubs, growing under them to thrive the better. Would you weed theſe ſcarlet poppies out of your Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes, without partiality, you would hardly find ſo many ſcarlet ſins reigning amongſt us: would you, I ſay
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:63490:18"/> but pull off this green and flouriſhing Ivy, which clings and hangs about the body of the Church, as if it lov'd and ſupported it, when indeed nothing leſs; I am ſure, the Church would flouriſh the better for it: I am far from the deſign of exaſperation; but this one thing more I muſt venture amongſt you, <hi>Let ſcandalous Great ones</hi> know, you ſtand as much upon your Conſciences, as they upon their ſuppoſed Honour; and indeed, its a ſhame to ſee them draw their Swords to juſtifie their Credit <hi>(ſuch as it is)</hi> and your ſelves, ſuch heartleſs Cowards in defence of your Conſciences, to keep them ſuch as they ſhould be: Remember, it's the notion of one greater than the greateſt of them all (no leſs a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon then our late Royal Maſter, in his <hi>Icon. Baſil.</hi> where he tells us, <hi>'Tis dangerous, very dangerous, gratifying any faction (much leſs ſuch a one as this) in a kingdom, to the violation of a known law:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have one errand more, and that's from the Dead, to you, the Church-wardens of our Pariſhes; and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, could the Dead be as effectually ſummon'd from their ſilent graves, as you have been from your houſes to attend this Viſitation, I doubt not, but that, many of them, would have met ſome of you here this day, with their juſter Preſentments and Complaints againſt you, not, for that they envy you the priviledges of the living, but, becauſe, Ah laſs! you'l ſcarce allow them, <hi>that</hi> of the Dead, I mean, of reſting from all their labours.</p>
            <p>Such are the ſcandalous ruins of ſome Churches and Chancels, and ſuch are the intolerable neglects of the conſecrated ground belonging to them; That the Dead can ſcarce lie dry, or ſafe from either: Oh Sirs! give the Dead their due, your Churches their juſt repairs, and your Church-yards, their decent Fences; Such as may be a better guard to the Dead, a better credit to the Living, and a greater comfort to your ſelves when dying: Remember, you all expect e're long, the Church, or it's Ground, muſt hide your nakedneſs, when you are dead; be then ſo juſt and good to them, as to hide their's, whilſt you are living.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:63490:18"/>
            <p>I ſhall now conclude with a ſhort and humble ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs to all my Reverend Brethren of the Clergie: and, oh that my words might live, when I am laid in my grave! You have all now given me the honour, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſerved patience of hearing me plead, and diſplay be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore your more knowing ſelves, the great influence and efficacy; together, with the great obligation, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of a religious exemplarineſs, on our parts eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially; And now, methinks, I ſee it in all your faces, a thing reſolv'd upon, <hi>viz.</hi> That this Auditory, and thoſe, you are going to; ſhall all ſee an happy and more particular enlargement upon the reſt of the Text, in the reſt of your lives: Methinks, I ſay, I now ſee you all, going out of <hi>this</hi> ſanctuary, as ſo many flaming Lamps, to your <hi>own,</hi> a freſh blown up and kindled by my weaker breath; Such, as may, by heavens bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction and aſſiſtance, fire and inflame your peoples hearts, with a greater zeal for God, and Religion in the life and efficacy of it;</p>
            <p>Such, as may make your people ſay, after your preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as they, after Chriſt ſpeaking<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Did not our hearts burn within us, whilſt he ſpake to us?</hi> Such, I ſay, as may convince all your unreaſonable and bitter adverſaries, That God is in and with you of a truth; and then, ſuch too, as may make the world (otherwiſe, prone enough to deſpiſe you) now really to love, and honour you all, for your being not only <hi>learned</hi> Preachers, but <hi>living</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terns too, and examples of Believers, in Word, in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, in Charity, in Spirit, in Faith, and in Purity; which God, in his mercy, grant, that you may all be, from this day of your Viſitation, to the day of your approaching death and Diſſolution.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:63490:19"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:63490:19"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 2 <hi>in marg.</hi> read <hi>contemplatione,</hi> p. 7. <hi>Lucelius.</hi> Line 27. for <hi>quis,</hi> r. <hi>qui,</hi> p. 9. l. <hi>Antepenult,</hi> for <hi>this,</hi> r. <hi>his,</hi> p. 14. l 28. for. <hi>form,</hi> r. <hi>for me. Epiſt. Ded.</hi> l. 2. for. <hi>in</hi> r. <hi>into the world.</hi> p. 6. l. 11. dele. <hi>in.</hi> p. 9. l. 36. for <hi>This,</hi> r. <hi>his people.</hi> p. 10. l. 8. dele. <hi>Them.</hi> p. 17. l. 1. ſor <hi>heard</hi> r. <hi>read ſomewhere,</hi> p. 18. l. 10. put in <hi>I come now to the</hi> fifth <hi>voice,</hi> put in the word <hi>fifth.</hi> p. 18. laſt line, for <hi>Honeſty,</hi> read <hi>Honey.</hi> pag. 20. line. 9. dele <hi>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſs.</hi> page 21 l. 2. put in <hi>it,</hi> profeſſing <hi>it.</hi> pag. 22. line. 15. for <hi>Siren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers,</hi> read <hi>Syringes.</hi> p. 22. l. 21. for <hi>knew,</hi> read <hi>know.</hi> p. 22. l. 36. read <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, p. 23 l. 13 for <hi>John</hi> 10.28. read, <hi>John</hi> 5.36: And read <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, p. 25. firſt line, dele <hi>Of the.</hi> page 25. line 17. read <hi>Mark</hi> 1 14. pag. 25. line 19 read <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. pag. 25. line 22. read <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> pag. 25. line 29. read <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, pag. 27. line 1. read <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, pag. 27. line 26. for <hi>the eyes,</hi> read <hi>your eyes.</hi> pag. 29. line. 25. read <hi>Timorous</hi> for <hi>Timerous.</hi> pag. 29. line 33. read <hi>lop.</hi> for <hi>top</hi> the lux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uriant branches. p. 30. read <hi>in,</hi> for, <hi>from either.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
